Guide to the Walter E. Fauntroy papers, 1941-1990 MS2070
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Walter E. Fauntroy papers, part 1
1941-1990
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Fauntroy, Walter E.
MS2070
30 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence, news releases, booklets, articles, brochures, statements, meeting files, briefing books, memorabilia, newsletters, photographs, negatives, slides, bills, and hearing files documenting the life and activities of civil rights activist Walter F. Fauntroy. These materials date from 1941-1990 with the bulk of the records falling between 1960-1990.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
In 1990, Walter E. Fauntroy donated his papers to The George Washington University Gelman Library.
Biographical Note
Walter E. Fauntroy was born in Washington, D.C. on February 6, 1933. He graduated from Dunbar High School in 1952 and received his Bachelor of Arts from Virginia Union University in 1955. He earned a bachelor of divinity from Yale University Divinity School in 1958. In 1959, he began his career in public service through his appointment as pastor of his childhood church, New Bethel Baptist Church. He served as pastor from 1959 until his retirement in 2009.
An advocate of civil rights, Fauntroy served as a leader in the civil rights movement. In 1960, Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., founder of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), appointed Fauntroy director of the Washington Bureau of SCLC. He remained in that position until 1971. As a director of SCLC, Fauntroy coordinated many historic events, including events leading up to the August 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom and the 1965 March from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama. In 1968, he served as the national coordinator of the Poor People's Campaign.
Fauntroy utilized his civil rights experience to promote urban redevelopment within the District of Columbia. He founded and served as the director of the Shaw Urban Renewal Project, and along with other Washington ministers, founded the Model Inner City Community Organization (MICCO), a neighborhood planning corporation. Fauntroy's active community involvement led to his first political position as the first vice chairman appointed to the District of Columbia Council in 1967. In 1969, Fauntroy resigned from the D.C. Council in order to focus more attention toward MICCO. Fauntroy's community service efforts and promotion of civil rights led him to work towards achieving rights for District residents. He became a vocal advocate for voting rights and representation within the District.
In 1970, Congress passed the Delegate Act enabling citizens of Washington D.C. to have representation in the United States House of Representatives. Subsequently in 1971, D.C residents elected Fauntroy to represent the District. Strongly supporting the right for full representation of the District, Fauntroy immediately began a legislative campaign in support of home rule. As a result, in 1973 the District of Columbia Self-Government and Government Reorganization Act became law. D.C. citizens were given the authority to elect a mayor and a city council. Fauntroy served in Congress for twenty years (1971-1991). He worked on many committees such as the Committee on the District of Columbia, the Committee Banking, Finance and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Banking, Currency and Housing, and the Committee on Banking and Currency. He also was part of the select committees on Assassinations, Narcotics and Control. He was a member of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, the Democratic National Congressional Committee, and the Congressional Black Caucus (CBC).
During his tenure in Congress, Fauntroy chaired several committees, such as the District of Columbia Committee's Subcommittee on Fiscal Affairs. While serving on the Committee on Banking, Finance and Urban Affairs, he chaired the Subcommittee on Domestic Monetary Policy and International Finance, Trade and Monetary Policy as well as a number of other subcommittees. He also served as the chairman for the CBC. Fauntroy utilized these committees to establish legislation in support of statehood for the District of Columbia. He founded the National Black Leadership Roundtable (NBLR), a network created under the auspices of the CBC, in support of domestic leadership. The "Free South Africa Movement" (FSAM) and the Congressional Task Force on Haiti serve as examples of Fauntroy's active involvement in international affairs. Under the direction of Fauntroy, NBLR developed and published The Black Leadership Family Plan for the Unity, Survival and Progress of Black People, and the Congressional Task Force on Haiti created United States policies that supported democracy, human rights promotion and economic development in Haiti.
The D.C. community has recognized and honored Fauntroy for his exemplary service. His alma maters awarded him with honorary doctor of divinity degrees. He received an honorary doctor of laws degree from Georgetown University Law Center for his leadership bringing the right to vote to the citizens of the District of Columbia. After delivering the Charter Day Convocation speech at Howard University in 1988, he was awarded the university's doctor of laws degree.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, news releases, booklets, articles, brochures, statements, meeting files, briefing books, memorabilia, newsletters, photographs, negatives, slides, bills, and hearing files. These materials date from 1941-90 with the bulk of the records falling between 1960-1990.
This collection of materials was generated during thirty-nine years of community, religious and political service. Fauntroy was an advocate of civil and political rights. A former congressman, Fauntroy served the people of the District of Columbia through various roles. Since 1959, Fauntroy has been the pastor of New Bethel Baptist Church. His exceptional leadership in community affairs led Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., founder of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), to appoint Fauntroy as the director of the Washington D.C. Bureau of SCLC. Through this position, he served as the coordinator of various historic events associated with the organization such as the 1963 March On Washington for Jobs and Freedom and the 1965 March from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama.
Fauntroy was the first vice chairman appointed to the Washington D.C. City Council. After years of promoting voting rights and representation for citizens of the District, Fauntroy served as the representative of Washington, D.C. in the United States Congress for twenty years. He was an advocate of urban renewal in the District of Columbia, and was a founder and director of the Shaw Urban Renewal Project and the Model Inner City Community Organization (MICCO).
By donating his papers to GWU, Fauntroy has enabled decades of community service through a collaboration of religious, civil and political activity to be treasured, researched and used for various educational purposes.
Fauntroy did not place any restrictions on the use of his papers. All rights and interests were transferred to the Department of Special Collections. In 1998, GWU retained The History Factory to organize, preserve and describe a select portion of his papers in anticipation of using some of the materials in the Library's exhibit on the 35th Anniversary of the 1963 March on Washington.
Collection Organization
Organized in six series: General files, Affiliations and organization files, Campaign files, Congressional committee files, New Bethel Baptist Church files, and Oversize files.
United States. Congress; Home rule; Urban renewal; Photographs; Political campaigns; Color slides; Black-and-white slides; March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom, Washington, D.C., 1963; Washington (D.C.); Civil rights; Fauntroy, Walter E.; Southern Christian Leadership Conference
- General files, 1960-1990; MS2070 Series 1; 9 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains meeting files, correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, negatives, slides, transparencies, news releases, brochures, speeches, newsletters, and subject reference files. These materials date from 1960-90. These records reflects reference files retained by Fauntroy and his congressional staff. Subjects include: agriculture, banking, civil rights, racial issues, urban renewal, public relations, and congressional activities.
  - Biographies, Walter E. Fauntroy, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Booklet, Legislation Sponsored by Fauntroy, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal and family file: Clippings, "Fauntroy's enjoy a First", 1971 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal and family file: Statement, Marvin Keith Fauntroy, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Address, Honoring Commissioner John B. Duncan, Baptist Ministers' Conference, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Address, 7th Annual Commencement Howard University, Howard University Commencement, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Address, Keynote Address to SCLC 10th Annual Convention, SCLC 10th Annual Convention, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Address, "War on Poverty", MCAC Rally, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Address, "Mastering the Arithmetic's of Politics", SCLC Announcing Political Strategy, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Address, Honoring Archbishop Helder Camara, Special Mass at St. Paul & Augustine Catholic Church, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Address, "Blacks & Jews", American University, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Address, "Of Walls and Bridges", Mackin High School Commencement, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Address, TransAfrica Annual Meeting, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Address, "Issue of Investment Policies For South Africa", Government Finance Officers Association's, Annual Meeting, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Address, "What Manner of Man?", Purdue University Peoples Day Program, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Address, "A Time to Repair, Rebuild and Re-establish a United and DetermiD.C.", 101st Congress Inauguration, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Address, " Housing Program for 101st Congress", Housing Now Press Conference, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Address, "State of the Nation's Last Colony East -West Tension and North -South Need", Beginning Session of 101st US Congress, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Address, "East-West Tension and North-South Need", Special Order U.S. House of Representatives, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Address, Women's National Democratic Club, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Address, Annual Dinner Dance United Negro College Fund, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Presentation, "Immigration Latin America, Human Rights, and The District of Columbia", Institute for Policy Studies, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Remarks, "Response to the President on Balanced Budget Amendment", Public Meeting on East Front Steps of The Capital Building, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Remarks, Support Tax Equity and Fiscal Responsibility Act of 1982, U.S. House of Representatives (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Remarks, International Cooperation Act of 1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Remarks, "House Resolution 20 The Federal Employees' Political Act", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Remarks, "Non -Dependence Day", American Lung Association, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Remarks, "Beautiful Breast-fed Babies Contest", The WIC State Agency, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Remarks, "Census As A Tool For Change", National Bar Association Mid-Year Conference, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Remarks, "House Resolution 1487", undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Remarks, "Support of House Resolution 6370", undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Speech, National Capital Planning Commission, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Speech, "Maiden Floor Speech", First Congressional Speech delivered to U.S. House of Representatives, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Speech, "On the Job Training", Meeting of the Department of Human Resources, Circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Speech, "Alliance, Participation and the Latino Community", Prismas, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Speech, "The Historical Crisis in Education and the Need for a Plan", District of Columbia Congress of Parents and Teachers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Speech, "The Case of the Haitian Refugees, The Immigration Reform and Control Act of 1983: Building A Constituency for the Black Immigrant", Conference on Immigration and the Changing Black Population (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Speech, Hyde Park Community Family Reunion, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Speech, "The Impossible Dream", University of Pennsylvania The George Dana Boardman Lectureship in Christian Ethics XXVII, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Speech, Eximbank's Annual Conference of Exporters and Bankers, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Speech, 78th Anniversary of the African National Congress, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Statement, "The Progress of Urban Renewal and Redevelopment in the District of Columbia", Interdenominational Ministers Alliance before the Senate Committees on the District of Columbia, Circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Statement, Free D.C. Movement, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Statement, `Proceedings and Debates of the 100th Congress", Congressional Record, 91st Congress, vol. 133, no. 99, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Statement, "1968 Election" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Statement, "RDC Rebuilding Effort", Circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Statement, "Need for Criminal Justice and Prison Reforms", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Statement, Liberation Train, March Against Repression, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Statement, Announcement for U.S. Congress Candidacy, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Statement, First Annual Conference of Household Workers, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Statement, "AFDC Program", National Urban League Hearings, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Statement, "Rent Control Act of 1973" (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Statement, "tax Reform; the Battleground of the Movement of the Seventies", Congressional Record, 98th Congress, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Statement, "Audit of D.C. Finances", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Statement, "Commuter Tax Bill Introduced by Congressman McKinney", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Statement, `Tax Upon Income Earin the District of Columbia by Nonresidents", Congressional Hearing on H.R. 11579, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Statement, "House Resolution 1540", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Statement, Inaugural Breakfast of the newly re-elected Council Members, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Statement, "Reciprocal Income Tax", The Subcommittee on Fiscal and Government Affairs of the House District Committee, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Statement, "Intention to Seek Re-election to Congress in 1978" (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Statement, "Support of House Resolution 3875", The Housing and Community Development Amendments of 1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Statement, "Shooting of President Reagan and the Atlanta Slayings", On the Floor of the House of Representatives, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Statement, "Congressional Legislation for the District of Columbia," During the 97th Congress, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Statement, "Fauntroy Amendment In The Nature Of A Substitute," House of Representatives, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Statement, League of Women Votes, Capital Area, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Statement, The Pepco P.A.C., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Statement, SEIU 1199 Health Care Leadership Conference, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Statement, "Which Would Establish A Foreign Missions Commission in the District of Columbia, U.S. House of Representatives, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Statement, "Criticizes the Department of Education's Decision to Halt Student Loans to 528 Post Secondary Educational Institutions", Black Churches and Black Colleges/Universities Network, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Statement, "Impact of Federal Reductions-In- Force", Manpower and Housing Subcommittee of the House Government Operations Committee, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Statement, "An Assessment of Where We Are", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Statement, "The Fauntroy Substitute to House Resolution 345," House of Representatives, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Statement, Fauntroy Town Meeting on the Economy and Employment, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Statement, Opening of Campaign Office, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Statement, "Endorsing The National Summit Conference on Black Economic Development and Survival", The National Summit Conference on Black Economic Development and Survival, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Statement, House Resolution 4853, Task Force on Haitian Refugees, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Statement, `Amendment to the Intelligence Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 1983, General Debate Statement (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Statement, "Three Reasons for Supporting of Nuclear Freeze and Other Arms-Control Measures", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Statement, " Social Security and Federal Retirement System", Town Meeting, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Statement, "Changing the Course and Lifting the Burden Through a Strong and Vigorous Ward and Precinct Organization", Congressional District Network, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Statement, "House Resolution 2817 and SUPERFUND Amendments of 1985", U.S. House of Representatives (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Statement, "Introduction of House Resolution 4026", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Statement, "Introduction of House Resolution 4746", U.S. House of Representatives, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Statement, "Amendment in the Nature of a Substitute to House Resolution 1", U.S. House of Representatives, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Statement, "Anti-Apartheid Act of 1986", U.S. House of Representatives (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Statements, "Washington Post Magazine Recall Committee Statement of Purpose", The Washington Post Magazine Recall Committee, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Statement, "17th African-American Conference in Botswana", Congressional Black Caucus, The National Black Leadership Roundtable, and the Free South Africa Movement Report, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Statement, "Response to Reagan's State of the Union Address", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Statement, "Living the Dream, Let Freedom Ring with Statehood for the District of Columbia, Second Annual National College and University Students Conference, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Statement, "Banking and Investment", Gulf America Conference, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Statement, D.C. Appropriations Bill, Town Meeting, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Statement, " Opening Statement for Atlanta Hearings", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Statement, "Foreign Affair Hearings", U.S. House of Representatives, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Statement, "Dr. Elizabeth Morgan Case", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Statement, "Judge Alcee Hastings Case", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Statement, "House Resolution 84", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Statement, "The Reauthorization Legislation for WMATA", Press Conference, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Statement, "Response to Introduction by Mr. Parris of a Bill to Provide for the Establishment of a National Capital Public Safety Administrator", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Statement, Youth Outreach Task Force, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Statement, " H.R. 20 Federal Employees Political Act of 1989", U.S House of Representatives (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Statement, "D.C. Police Authorization and Expansion Act of 1989", U S. House of Representatives (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Statement, "China Hearing", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Statement, "Hearing on Rescheduling South Africa's Debt", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Statement, "Laventhol and Horwath Study of Kenilworth-Parkside", The Fauntroy Legislation Program, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Statement, "House Resolution 3470", Before The Subcommittee on Judiciary and Education Committee, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Statement, "Response to Indictment of Mayor Marion S. Barry", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Statement, "Following His Meeting with City Administrator Carol Thompson", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Statement, "Oversight Hearings-Resolution Trust Corporation", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Statement, "Neighborhood Redevelopment in the District of Columbia," Public Meeting, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Statement, "Appointment of Alfred David Jones", Committee on Public Services, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Statement, "Support of Amendment to Second Supplemental D.C. Appropriations Bill", undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Statement, Candidacy of Banks, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Statement, "D.C. Convention Center Controversy", undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Statement, "D.C. Temporary Curfew Law", undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Statement, "Endorsing Johnny Barnes for D.C. Council", undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Statement, "Epilogue", Financial Plan and Issues Platform, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Statement, "House Resolution 7144", U.S. House of Representatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Statement, Opposition to Burton Amendment Striking Funds Earmarked for Economic Aid to SADCC", U.S. House of Representatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Statement, Personnel Practices Investigation, Justice Department, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Statement, Retirement Health Benefits Symposium, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Statement, "War on drugs," Wayne Hall, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Statement, "Working Together to Implement the Plan", Congressional District Network for Legislative Action, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Statement, "The Washington Agenda", undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Testimony, " Re-Opened Washington-Baltimore Helicopter Investigation", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Testimony, "Proposing a Rule to Permit An Amendment to the Continuing Resolution", Before the Rules Committee, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Tribute, "Joseph Boyce McCormick, The Quite Diplomat", U.S. House of Representatives, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Tribute, "A Tribute to Marion H. Jackson", U.S. House of Representatives, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Tribute, " A Tribute to Harold James Cook", U.S. House of Representatives, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Article, "The Y Emblem", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Article, "The Black Church", 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Article, DFSC Information Bulletin, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Article, Minority Supplier News, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Article, Hubert H. Humphrey Humanitarian Award, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Article, The Metro Chronicle, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Article, Tenant Management, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Article, Letter to the Editor, Circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, Selma, Mississippi, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, Activism, 1966-1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, Fauntroy Social and Business, 1969-1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, D.C. Rent Control, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, Southern Election Fund, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, D.C. Mayoral Campaign, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, Crime, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, Congressional Sports, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, Economy, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, International Politics, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, D.C. Politics, 1972-1990 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, Maryland and Virginia Politics, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, Federal Government, 1977-1989 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, District of Columbia, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, Education, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, Election, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, Klu Klux Klan, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, Louis Farrakhan, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Clippings, NAACP, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, Poverty, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, Banking, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, Russia, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, D.C. Social Issues, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 31)